all right welcome to special birthday
edition of idea camp held two hours
earlier that's why I'm dressed as a
giant unicorn although I think I've worn
this to other ones as well at least you
are a mega rule I've worn some joint one
this easy to today's question has a bit
of like a pre which is like we've made
it to game B every you know we have all
those Omni win anti rivalry most
solutions whatever time period you think
that happens and hopefully within your
lifetime because we're asking what does
your life look like in that'd be a
pretty quick five minute share if it's
like oh I'm gonna coffin because it took
us two years but maybe your next
lifetime then maybe what your next life
side looks like if you believe in
reincarnation so who would like to start
I can be really really really quick I
can be super quick here I'm joining
Starfleet I think that Star Trek world
is a pretty good picture of what game be
world looks like right you know we don't
use money we work to better ourselves
and to expand the knowledge and
awareness of humanity know what I mean
that and so that's what I would do I
would join Starfleet I've always wanted
to go into space if indeed space does
exist I've always wanted to go there so
that's me
because actually mines mines pretty
similar except that I think that it
doesn't communicate as deeply as I as I
want to do and I would say just to add
some layers to that the relational
technology psycho technology and digital
technology work together but the the
sense of what it is that we're working
to accomplish towards a true collective
intelligence and I and I say that and it
sounds still sounds a little bit sci-fi
II I have us I have a specific
interpretation of what that means which
is kind of holographic intelligence my
own individual intelligence make sense
the collective intelligence makes sense
and I work between those and you know I
find ways to express myself and to
connect to deeper desires of what's
wanted to be done right now that this
sense of collective
I'll just looks a little bit too much
like the board where I have to give up
my own sovereignty in order to align
with mega sovereignty and and and I
don't think that's necessary but so in
the game be world that that the portals
between individual peer to peer and peer
to collective make much more sense and
we have communication strategies and
practices for dealing with that more
effectively thank you do you want to go
branch you want me to go I can go mm-hmm
just to build off Eric's point ie I said
to somebody yesterday what we're trying
to do is build Starfleet not Skynet
right that's that's the fundamental
distinction and you know you could say
you could put the Borg in there to to
David's point like it's um it's the same
principle right it's technology turned
against us mm-hmm and I mean this is
oversimplifying but that's what it comes
down to right and and and when I was
talking about that I highlighted the
next generation to as the kind of stent
standout Star Trek series because it was
so much more about peace and diplomacy
and what what social relations look like
in a post-scarcity world right so there
wasn't so much violence and and the
violence was was was not repressed but
but transmuted into conflicts that they
could solve in courtrooms or whatever
right and then occasionally it would
still come to violence because that's
just the nature of entertainment and and
addiction and and and in reality to some
extent
other than that though my game be world
looks like you know somewhat like
University just but despite its current
flaws you know everyone has access to
education and free speech and hmm
you know there's sort of higher purpose
you're driving towards and so obviously
universe
in a tough place and we need to um you
know challenge how that's being eroded
by neoliberalism but but generally you
know you want it you want to expand out
that's that kind of template rather than
constrict it and have it be a very
exclusive place and a place where free
speech is actually weaponize is to
further you know anti progressive goals
um I think I think the you know whatever
game be is in the future it looks very
different from how it is today as well
when there's a lot of internal tension
and and hypocrisy and a silencing and
and blocking and alliances and all these
sorts of things at the expense of
converging on some truly higher
principles I'll just leave it there for
in it intro right let's see if I can get
through mine without coffee or that's
probably not gonna happen
alright so I living within the game be
space where we've actually gotten to the
point where we are
Omni win and ante rival risk I think we
don't even know what that looks like
like what you said about Star Trek The
Next Generation being peaceful and based
on peace and then a lot of the other
ones are based on war mainly for
entertainment because that's what we are
that's the drama that drives our society
that our lack of imagination in that
area like it's almost like we think it's
going to be boring it's going to be
boring to live in a world where we've
eliminated poverty and we're now
connected in this collective
intelligence or we maintain our personal
autonomy where I get to be my unique
individual self whatever that means
meaning I have to accept everyone else
also where they are with of course a few
caveats no you know that's murder you
know like they are murder at all zero
murder you I don't think you ever get to
but we get to the vast vast vast
reduction and then new drama emerges
like the the your interpret your inter
and intra personal drama doesn't go away
we figure out how to how to be in how to
be whole individuals and how to be in
small groups and this big big meta group
that I don't think so within that space
when we're actually in game be my life
looks like living in a smaller village
where we're growing food together where
I don't have to do all the labor but I
get to experience being with the animals
being with the plants eating that food
and working on projects are important to
me that actually have nothing to do with
that I just really want that to be the
foundation of the community that I live
in I want to spend my days riding horses
and being in nature and having
conversations that help me advance and
help whatever projects I am I'm working
on with other people advance as well and
even within this space like when I ask
people what they would do if they won
the lottery or what they would do if
game becomes about a lot of what they're
in is still rival race and antivirus
both in a in a in a like negative way
and in a positive way like oh I would
help the poor there aren't a core to
help what are you gonna spend your time
doing oh that doesn't exist anymore
right like because I do think when we
find the way to work together we cure
99% of cancer we stop and cure 99% of
cancer we stop Alzheimer's we stop these
things that we can't do by ourselves
and so when we figure out how to work
together without getting along we then
are able to create game be very rapidly
and that part of that is accepting like
I me and I have to accept other people
where they are and where there's
conflict do we work it out and grow or
do we separate each other and I think
there's room for both in that space and
now I'm getting into other other topics
but that is I guess my answer today of
where I would be in in game B so thank
you know we have hey all four of us
shared under 10 minutes that's I'd
really like to just jump in here and
pick up on from where
Jubilee has just left off and tie it
together with the whole Star Trek next
generation thing as well I'm reminded of
an episode I think there's just
connection also nicely I'm reminded of
an episode where I comment what his name
was it was the guy that played Murdock
in the a-team I can't remember Berkeley
that's hit Berkeley he gets an addiction
to the holiday right and but the point I
want to make is that at no moment in
their episode was there any kind of you
know condemnation or vilification or
exclusion of him straight away the thing
was how can we help him right what's
gone wrong how can we help him be the
deep assumption is this is a good guy he
signed up at the st. to Starfleet that
we all did right and so you know there
there was never even a question of
there's something wrong with him right
there's it's how can we all
fundamentally wrong with him right but
that something has gone wrong how can we
help and I like that that kind of thing
happens a lot in the Star Trek universe
they are in the next-generation universe
anyway as you correctly pointed out it
is by far and away the best of the
iterations of Star Trek and yeah and I
just think it fits really nicely with
what Jubilee was saying as well about
meeting everyone where they are right
you are you and you have every right to
be all of you that you can be but so the
fuck does everybody else right and this
is I like what was it you said figuring
out ways to work together without
getting along I really I really like
that that's exactly that that captures
it really nicely mm-hmm yeah beautiful
example Eric what the very last thing
you said though it makes me think of you
know politicians who who really stretch
to reach both sides of the aisle you
know that that that that are proud of
how they work with both sides and I
think of Joe Biden you know for exactly
that because he's just a friendly hand
shaker he'll he'll he'll you know build
all these bridges or whatever but but
there are some of them are really toxic
relationships right like like we're
we're in this reactionary age and
you know there's that there's the kind
of controversy that's recent of like
Ellen being friends with George Bush
right that's one thing we can we can
come from come from compartmentalize
that but then what about you know people
in people liberals being friends with
people in the Trump administration you
know like how how far do we stretch it
and how how absurd do we twist the
reality to like the story rather to mask
the reality right um so but yeah there's
just sort of a paradox that I wanted to
pick up on you know we need to support
people like Berkeley but uh you know
yeah you know try not to compromise or
work with double-crossers those types of
things right because Berkeley was a good
guy but some other people have deeper
flaws or ulterior motives so I hope that
makes sense just in the in the case of
centrist politics and I think like where
you take the diversity even like the
binary of the left and the right and
instead of honoring the different pieces
they both bring you kind of like average
them out you don't get anything that's
not diversity right like when you're and
yet we need we need centralize when you
bright when you've left we need all of
the diversity that exists and so in the
case of like Ellen and George Bush yeah
they get to be friends cuz George Bush
gets to be George Bush and Ellen gets to
be Ellen and they get to decide if
they're friends but there's a larger
question of the you know LGBT like
people who are anti LGBT and are like
well you can't exist and people who are
LGBT like there's conversations to be
had on the individual level where are
like yeah I have conservative family and
friends that I love and yet calling them
out on their shit isn't actually helping
them advance and it took me 20 years to
figure that out right I'm like oh
there's ways I can engage in this with
love and understanding that actually
gets you to see it and there's ways that
are just confrontational that are just
gonna make you dig your heels in deeper
and I'm not honoring you
I'm not seeing who you are what does
George Bush bring right what into the
world and yet there is a power structure
that needs to be looked at right
George Bush B and George Bush isn't the
problem it's that George Bush gets to be
President and and inflict those
throughout right like it's the power of
who's there yet everyone who voted for
him is exactly where they're supposed to
be right like they're their own
individual self and if that's where they
feel their best chance is then of course
they're gonna go for him like there
needs to be a way of honoring the
individual and asking like why did you
vote for George but like when we figure
out that met a piece of intelligence
where we can actually understand what
politicians stand for and it's not all
spin and it's not all sociopaths in
charge then we can kind of allow
sociopaths to exist right like when
you're not our CEOs and presidents they
can exist there's a space for them
they're actually a really important
piece of society I don't know what cuz
I'm not like I don't know actually what
that piece is but there's something
there or they wouldn't exist but they're
not supposed to be in charge of
countries and corporations and we're not
supposed to like prop that up to this
degree it's a so like you just pop in
and say it's it's tricky right and one
way because you know love him or hate
him and both right Steve Jobs is kind of
one of those sociopaths that did move he
did did the universe for better or worse
you know there are there are a lot of
good things and bad things so it's
there's something about the kind of
gutsiness
that allows somebody to say I'm going to
do something impossible you know
Elon Musk's and and Bill Gates in the
you know the the people of the world who
do say you know I'm going to do this and
it and then they pull together the
resources and the coordinating people in
order to get things then I think what I
think what I see in a game would be
world is the the discrepancy between how
much influence individuals at the top
end of the pyramid and the bottom end
have that it actually doesn't flatten to
level that's not the point but that it
has with
domains you know the recognition is that
you you are an expert in some field and
so that it really does that's kind of
what I mean by holographic there is a
way in which we don't have to view it
through one common lens of this is the
one true truth of the whole world right
and my in this community we operate a
little bit differently than we do in a
larger world and in some way it feels
refreshing because we have found tribe
members who feel who think of things
similarly and it's like I could not have
these kinds of conversations and they're
in the bigger world and I wouldn't want
to have a world where everybody should
be having the conversation same way we
are but we find each other and and find
a way to have those conversations so
there's so it's an interesting kind of a
it's an interesting notion and I think
what you said Julie we can't really
envision what that looks like in its
full expression so it also becomes less
possible you know I I don't know how
many of you are familiar with the like a
meeting technology called them open
space technology but it's you know you
can move from place to place so you
can't like Bogart a room and say okay
this is I'm going to take us all in this
direction if you don't like the way the
conversations going go somewhere else
you know and so I think that there are
ways that things like that can work and
less hijacking and and when when there's
not the ability to hijack there's also
not the ability there's not not the need
to police I think I talked about that I
don't know if it was that exact same
technology but when I talked to Jordan
Hall he had mentioned that what I was
doing the idea cafe and we was like well
there's this one where you walk in and
out of rooms and I love that concept I
think there is a piece of it I don't
like that I think we can deal with in
the overall picture which is like if I
don't if I'm not getting along with
friends if if like we have a diabolical
opposition that we're just really I can
choose to not be at a table with him and
not have a conversation and that's fine
there's no neither of us can do it all
so we can work on that and grow as human
beings but it has to be consensual by
both parties but
if I then go Eric you're not allowed to
work with Brent and David you're not -
or just through peer pressure you know
what I mean I'm like I'm leaving who's
with me there's a difference in like if
I'm offended or upset or whatever I'm
going through myself and I can honor
that that's my shit right even if it's
if it's currently manifesting as a
relationship with Brent what like that I
can pull myself back without me and
everyone else to join me and not making
you if I'm capable in that space in the
moment not making Brent wrong about it
either right like he's who he is
we are just diabolically opposed at the
moment and I'm sorry for picking you
brand sorry but I think there's another
really important part to this I mean
with this game fact this came up in a
conversation we had about rural Omega
Jubilee and I heard Bonita Roy talk
about this as well that the clash of
difference is an opportunity for
originality you know what I mean for
something truly original and creative to
be to be found and so you know in the
example that you've given where you and
Brent simply can't find a way to get on
you know it comes up room after room
after room with the two of you are in
there the argument between you dominated
conversation right
I would suggest rather than avoiding
each other the two of you should get
into a room and figure out what it is
you know I mean because there's there's
I feel like there's rich potential for
discovery in in a dynamic such as that
right if you can unpick the the negative
aspects which are blocking the ability
to communicate then and then I think
that there could be real fruit to be
found underneath that you know I agree
both agreed to that right that's where
it's like if we need time apart we need
time apart if we like what we probably
shouldn't and can't do is keep showing
up in rooms and dominating the
conversation with that conflict right
then neither of us are going to be
invited to the room you know and like
everyone's gonna leave the room every
time and literally leave us there by
ourselves which is like oh I guess we
did that right I guess we created the
space to deal with the conflict between
us somehow I think you know it's
important to point out that that often
the the the whatever the conflict is it
just gets repressed or sublimated and
pushed somewhere else if you don't deal
with it appropriately right that's why
things like terrorism you know or or
white supremacy II come up and erupt
because they're under the surface all
the time and you know if we're fighting
for like a post-conflict sort of society
and and protocol mmm-hmm
you know we're not gonna get there if if
we're not handling conflict properly
right now you know and and this is why
I've been like really critical of
intellectual dark web types and and and
their and their interlocutors because
there's not a lot of conflict conflict
resolution there's a lot of patting each
other on the back there's a lot of
saying controversial things that that
that could totally be mediated by some
other information or another another
person you know there's a lot of
sensationalism there's a lot of
attacking and I try not to attack people
like critique right and then I get
attacked because people don't know the
difference
but uh but but you know I agree with you
your guys's sentiments that we have to
find ways to go through you know we have
to go through and and if it is a stark
situation like if you have two racist
really rate one racist person and one
really progressive person if you could
just you know bring them together mm-hmm
and in with what their what their
consent and in the right sort of
environment then then it would resolve
it can resolve itself you know there's
plenty of examples of this so I have a
question for you bright because you had
mentioned you'd alluded to the in
terrestrial dark web and that they I
don't know what you called it you said
that you critique and what was the other
word that they attack attack what is
because you said they don't know the
difference what is the difference um so
you know critique isn't is in the
academic sense means you're you're
you're carrying out a process which you
know deconstruction is one part of it
you're trying to UM like you know uh you
know read between the lines and and
interpolate what the author means and
what the context is and all these things
but but you know critique in that in
this sense is part of a broader
tradition right of of truth-seeking a
free-thinking but but by and large what
you're doing when you critique is you're
pointing out something that's that's
untrue or wrong and that and that can be
identified clearly and isolated you know
and a lot of academic work you know
especially what we call postmodern like
it's very critical and it kind of it
often stops at critique you know it
doesn't it doesn't necessarily have the
solution for the given problem but it's
but it's done everything they can to
deconstruct you know hundreds of years
of history and discourse and distill it
into a salient observation that can move
that critical discourse forward attack
couldn't look very similar but it but it
would be motivated for different reasons
it would have different tactics it would
you know could often include a lot of ad
hominem type stuff and the ad hominem
fallacy can go both ways to like you can
you can uh you know make a comment about
someone's character and it can it can
totally undermine your own your own
thesis you know you could be committing
a fallacy but you can also make a
comment about someone's character that
is that is legitimately tied to the
question right so if I make a remark
about Trump that is that seems nasty or
derogatory like there's a context there
in which that personal attack is coupled
with my with my greater critique right
so it's not always clear that it's a
fallacy if you if you insult or label
somebody um but that's I I don't know I
hope that helps clarify the people I
think there's there's certainly
something there like I know what I'm
trying to do and get out into the world
I recently had someone like critique me
on my on my youtube channel I was like
oh thanks for helping me clarify this I
don't give it what you think about me as
a human being I don't need your opinion
on me I don't need you to tell me to
show up in a different way or what to do
me
but the idea critique the idea I'm down
with critiquing the idea all day and you
can critique me I'm just not gonna
listen I don't care I don't you know
unless you're someone who's put in time
and put in even then probably like it
has to come from within I think a lot of
whether it's critique like what people
say about Trump I just like Trump I
think he's a horrible president I also
in there like he's fat his hands are
small he's orange I'm like that's not
helpful and you're not only critiquing
him in fact you're hurt like you're also
bullying everyone who is like him right
in that way right everyone who's orange
is bad everyone who's you know it has an
extra few extra pounds everyone who you
know is can't think of the right thing
in the right in the right moment like
critique his actual evil acts in or
Namie like the actual things he's done
in the outcomes that have happened but
it's hard to do when you feel a fronting
right you're like you're like right
people I know have been deported people
I know have been hurt right like this is
it this isn't then you start critiquing
or attacking which is there's a
different sense I want to add to because
you know I put I put my my I
self-published a lot of my articles on
medium and often when I get into
disputes with people I ask them for
proper critique I invite it and medium
is a good platform to do that because
you can make private comments you can
highlight etc and it allows me to revise
the the article people almost never do
that right and somebody told me this
morning that right now I'm being
attacked in an integral Facebook group
and and it's one of these uh spin-off
integral groups that's like a little
more sexist and whatever then then then
than others but I'm being attacked in
there right now and I can't even see it
I don't have access but see those people
are engaging with the substance of my
work at all they're offended because
I've critiqued integral and not only am
i critiqued integral I you know I
basically surveyed the landscape of
integral critiques where you know many
other people and and in those articles I
have over 60 citations
many people have critiqued integral like
this isn't new this isn't news there's
been a huge schism lots of fallout and
yet you know people have Ken Wilber
Wilber on their podcasts and who pretend
like none of that history happened you
know they just want Wilbur to weigh in
on on the intellectual dark web or on
politics and it's just empty a kind of
conversation at that point like we're
not we're not getting anywhere because
the critiques haven't been processed and
in response people are just attacking
each other
can we ever protest for tips though no
just in terms of the difference between
attack and critique because I'm not for
me anywhere I don't think either of you
have quite honed in on it i Brent you
sort of alluded to it but I think a
critique seeks to be constructive right
it seeks to point out the flaws in
something so that a deeper level of
understanding can occur right this is
where you've gone wrong and maybe I have
some solutions or maybe I don't I don't
think offering solutions is necessary to
a critique so long as the point is to
constructively point out failings right
whereas an attack constructive or not is
irrelevant right the purpose of an
attack is to bring the person down yet
to make the person smaller or to make
the idea smaller not for reasons of
improving it but for reasons of seeking
victory over it right but in some other
way I think I think this is the it's it
this is the crucial difference between a
critique and an attack in my view yeah a
lot of I'll let you go but a lot of a
lot of this academic critique is
constructive in the sense and academics
if they parse it correctly they
appreciate it and they and it moves the
discourse forward but it doesn't always
go that way go ahead David
well it's interesting I noticed that
there's a couple of I've participated in
early days of knowledge management
knowledge of knowledge science
discussions there were primarily
academic in the tone there was did feel
very much critical at a point of like
walking right up to the line of ad
hominem you know just almost calling you
an idiot for believing something so
inane has this right but it's an in it
in it was it was difficult to read but
you know then that could notice that
actually they're not taking offense at
each other when they do that that's kind
of the environment that's the way that's
the culture that they have with each
other so there's something in that that
that's kind of understood and it's not
in the broader audience so that the
difference between critique and attack
can be more difficult to discern but but
I'll say there's something else that's
really kind of intriguing here I've been
reading the book by Donald Hoffman
called the case against reality and and
there's an interview that he did that
was a very fascinating interview which
he said we like to think that reason is
useful because it helps us get to the
truth and he said I don't think that's
actually the purpose of reason the
purpose of reason is to get larger
numbers of a group of people to agree
with each other in the way of it's an
evolutionary benefit because we need to
coordinate our actions and so if someone
is persuasive they align collectives
more and that's effective and we respond
positively to that and in a way this is
it's to confuse that with truth gets
into the place where if I disagree with
what you're saying it feels like you're
attacking my truth and that starts to
feel personal even if it's a critique
and it's an interesting thing to notice
it's like when I look at it one of the
other examples that he gives in that is
the jewel beetle in Australia that is
attracted to beer bottles and almost
went extinct because the beer bottles
look like the female and the beetles
preferred to mate with beer bottles
rather than the natural females so in
some way you could say the same thing of
a human beings we are attracted to
debate even when it doesn't actually get
us closer to truth and so we end up
trying to make with this with this
ideology it's like and that's not gonna
actually produce anything that's only
that's only doing something to our brain
chemicals but it's actually not moving
the
important so this this is one of the
reasons I like John drove a key and his
view of wisdom cultivation and looking
at how do we avoid bullshit and
self-deception
on an individual level in a collective
level and it's a very challenging thing
to do especially given that that
perspective yeah I love that David
because there's there's a piece of I'm
loved debate debates I enjoy being in
one or at least I did and it was very
much that it was like getting my truth
right like like convincing you of my
siding quite frankly when I was good at
it I could do I could convince you of
either side and it's like well that's
not actually looking for the truth and I
think that what I was I don't remember
what Brent had said I was like well how
do we actually do that like like moving
the discourse forward I don't think we
ever moved the discourse forward all
because there is no like we can have a
debate on climate change and no matter
what we came to it's not actually gonna
move the climate forward right like it's
not actually gonna move that it'll move
us forward as individuals you know what
I mean like we might change our idea but
it's like people who are like do your
research I'm like what is the freaking
point you could spend thousands of hours
doing your research and you still the
other person didn't do that research and
they don't trust you like there's
seeking the truth and finding ways to
look at what is true and how much
evidence is there for this side how much
evidence is for this side including the
very beautiful gray space of right
there's always evidence for both sides
even the here's what that evidence is
and then like then that's actually
helpful this is kinda the whole problem
with debate though isn't it is that
there are only ever two propositions on
the table in opposition to each other
there is no room for new propositions to
emerge during the course of the debate
and for both sides oh you know what
that's a fucking much better idea than
either of them you know this this is the
fundamental restrictive nature of debate
as opposed to discussion I mean
good-faith discussion between
knowledgeable open-minded people
actually willing to change their view
during the course of the discussion
you're in this this is how you get
closer to truth debates are exactly as
David said they're they're they're its
masturbation it's
intellectual masturbation is all it is
really there there is no striving for
truth in that format in my opinion yeah
I can add to this and it's especially if
you take debate just by itself right
that it's that it's dysfunctional and
and that's largely what we've done in
society and there's this model of debate
dialogue and deliberation which sort of
takes the three together you know and
then there then the flaws of you cancel
each other out like like there's
problems with direct democracy to where
people just vote on everything and have
a direct say-so you know you need to
have debates but also deliberation and
dialogue right and it creates this more
complex kind of methodology to foster
and generate higher truths right and and
like you're saying I think debates by
themselves uh might take us backwards in
many cases something there's something
here that's really kind of interesting
and brynn want to challenge you a little
bit and in generally like I noticed
there's that there's something about the
quality of the interaction between us
for this different imagine if David
fuller had dialed in and was part of
this conversation when he spoke your
response to him would I don't know I
don't know this but my guess is that
there would be something of the previous
interaction that you've had that would
come into this conversation for sure
first it would be and it would be
challenging to actually meet the merit
of the discussion on the table because
wait a minute I don't care what you're
saying now what you said of the past
invalidates that and there's something
about that which seems to challenge the
clear distinction between attacking and
critiquing so there's something in that
that that so I mentioned that as kind of
a as a point that is an interesting
thing to notice and then also that
there's something that I have imagined
happening in a game be world I have an
internal model that we're moving to kind
of an adult space
I say adult I mean mature that in a in a
kind of a growing space there is
more attacking debating kind of a model
we are we do respond like mating beetles
when debate happens and get confused
whereas if you get to a level of
maturation where it's like okay it's not
all about sex it's I'm not gonna be
distracted by the debate tactics I'm
actually gonna see what are the issues
are we moving anything is there a new
idea of emerging out of this discussion
and there's something that I feel that
is possible with that it's a challenge
we're in it we feels like we're in a
transitionary period and so even in like
the game be Facebook group where it
blows up all kinds of stuff happened it
looks to me on the surface just like
something that happened in the past with
flame wars in the early days but it
actually has it looks like we're also
developing a kind of collective immune
system for how to deal with this it's
early days so it still has flaws but it
starts to move towards trying to figure
out how do we actually do this without
getting off into other shape yeah I
think I think that's right part of my
problem and this is gonna make me sound
[Music]
hmm kind of like a snob or whatever but
I don't I don't care it's that a lot of
people in these groups I kind of expect
more from them and that's a compliment
you know like like in one sense what you
said is absolutely true like we're still
just figuring this out like it's just
emerging like you know we have we have
to kind of trust the process but on the
other hand like a lot of this stuff goes
back 10 years and it's like it wasn't
i'muh or or or much longer of course
like 50 years before I was even born um
you know and and it comes to these these
uh mm-hmm
not intersections but kind of um kind of
you know collisions where things in the
past just weren't adequately addressed
and it's like well I I told you so like
this this was a ticking time bomb you
know and I think I think right now
what's going on race is one of those
issues and it ties directly into the
intellectual dark web stuff because they
bought into the
the idea hook line & sinker that social
justice is toxic a religion a
counterproductive etc right there are
critiques that we can make about social
justice right from within sociology and
that's and that's my kind of prerogative
but to have like this uh you know pretty
uniform right-wing movement just wash
over the entire political spectrum with
this anti social justice Dogma which you
know if we go back to occupy a you know
social justice warrior was kind of a
German term of endearment you know
before it became a very toxic thing it
was like this um you know idea of a
person risking themselves personally for
a higher cause and and really that there
is no kind of direct personal benefit in
that and now there's this idea that
those people are just like Fame seekers
or whatever and hmm you know it's a bit
backward so just to bring it a
background of the point it's like you
know Vienna Gupta is is describing
what's going on and game be as soft
racism right and he's got his argument
built out for that you know I would I
would draw attention to a different term
white ignorant you know in all these
debates and they are debates that we've
seen in the public you know there's a
fixation on terms like white fragility
and stuff like this and a lot of just
trying to debunk that whole discourse
but there's you know if you're if you're
trained in sociology if you're
interested in these things if you have a
kind of wide perspective of the
landscape there's so much research out
there it's so nuanced you know this this
idea of white ignorant comes from a
black sociologist named Charles W Mills
and it's I mean I think it's brilliant
but when you try to share that with
people they get defensive right and so
it's like we're for white people here
talking about game B again and it's like
uh you know in some sense we should
already know better because a lot of
this is out there but on the other hand
like you say David like we're just on
the cusp of you know or the threshold
and actually
you know the internet getting to where
it is by this time in 2020 like many
people are getting access for the first
time to all this information and a lot
of academic stuff is still behind
paywalls
that I have access to and lots of other
people don't right so there's all sorts
of epistemic gaps that ends up turning
people against each other and against
the discourse which is the kind of
critical process of inquiry into these
things and then and then you know it
blows up and it's and then you know I'm
sitting here and I'm like well of course
it blew up it's like you didn't you
didn't properly integrate in the first
place what these other discourses had to
contribute in fact it's been kind of
pushed away I just wanted to UM when
David had first started talking about
other David in you forgot his name sorry
fuller um and it brought to mind this ID
they how like if he was here you would
bring your history into it and you guys
have had two negative interactions since
you both bring that into whatever space
you're in and as a parent to my child
like I could never have more love for
another human being and I have never had
more conflict with another human being
yet I don't bring that into the next day
right I don't bring in um well yesterday
you didn't listen to me
right she might she's seven right like
she might be like well yesterday you
would yeah that was yesterday like I
show up differently and my worst I am
NOT the most compassionate and I freaked
out and I'm like my nervous system is on
edge and I yell you know like I sound
bitchy and yet in my when I'm at my best
I can be present with her when she's a
tornado and and be the calm and I think
we all have moments of whether there's
love there or not we have moments where
we show up poorly and moments where we
show up well and just like the Star Trek
or you know the guy was a dick to the
holograph they knew he was a good guy
bringing that back in repeatedly like
just cuz someone did one thing wrong
that doesn't mean ignore it it but like
keep bringing it back to that same point
again and again keeps bringing that back
in as opposed to like where can we find
the common ground here and I also the Ln
George Bush thing I think there's a
really big difference cuz I don't know
if they're friends like are they hanging
out on Sunday I think they like saw each
other and abend and she didn't slap him
in the face it's very different in
person and on video to come off
confrontational
then in type or one you're reading into
every like we can get much more
information by tone of voice and you
know then we can in written word and so
you like someone type something we make
it mean something and it goes you know
it goes back and forth and risk there
was something about the risk that you
would mention the Occupy movement and
how with social justice back during that
time period it was a risk to take that
on and now that everyone's kind of come
on board and it becomes the like meta
society it's actually risky to not be
right not not to go back to racism
because that's risky to for sure like to
go back to pre social justice is risky
but so is to go beyond it to say there's
this doesn't quite get to it like police
in everyone's language isn't actually
helping us evolve it's not helping
people be less racist less homophobic
it's just covering it up and it's coming
out in every other way and so all of
those people are right like if you're in
racism you truly can't see that the
social justice piece and when you're in
social justice you can't see that other
piece and that is something Ken Wilber
all his faults has given me is that pre
trans policy of like when you're in the
middle the for the this looks the same
right these people who've gone beyond
social justice look like the Ku Klux
Klan right and they're not they're like
wait there's more nuance here there's
more and yet we do need to have those
conversations that work for white people
talking about game B needs to be
discussed and discussed more option and
the gender and the ability and like all
of that but also are the four of us
gonna solve racism we have other things
to solve like not the racism doesn't
need to be solved that's huge but like
we're can't even see it
in it so like those people those people
do need to solve it and ask for help
instead of just like it's wrong do
better
what does better look like because how
and I'm gonna butcher is name if I say
it showed up in the game beast face
wasn't great I am all for like we need
to keep having these conversations and
like yes people are dying in the world
is burning its poor and people of color
who are getting the vast majority of the
outcome but then let's empower them
because he's also rich right he actually
has more power than I do he could
actually create the thing that I have in
my head he's creating his own thing it's
like it isn't you don't get to like
stamp your social justice thing on
everything right like Ray says I'm here
it's like you do because that's you as a
human being but also like what about
ableism it's everywhere what about
classism right like all this like well
it has to you first need to succeed a
game a before you can participate in
game B or suck so badly at it you're
kind of on disability right like or you
know like that that level and we need to
be working in all areas all of them
which means my job maybe isn't racism
but I can't stand in the way of the
people who are doing it I'm sorry I
think I've talked for a long time yeah I
think those are really good points and
it's again it's nuanced and complex in
the way that we deal with this in some
way you know I want to go back to
earlier and looking at I loved Brett
when you mentioned about education needs
to change and again you know there's
something that my my view is that
everything that we see from our
perspective right now colors the
potential that we see in the future in a
way that minimizes it way beyond what an
actual what the actual potential is so I
see education as being more specialized
to people's interests and abilities very
very hyper focused on on certain things
while maintaining you know a general
competency but we have so much so much
that's included that general sameness in
a standardized way that we miss the
brilliance and genius of the potential
that could be developing in individuals
and it's a I think the the waste of that
is
huge and clearly now it seems like you
are outweighing you know the scales have
tipped in me and the balance in the
opposite direction that we're now
harming ourselves rather than benefiting
ourselves and technology allows us to do
something like that but it's tricky as
well because as you start to be able to
differentiate different educational
modalities and groups and things like
that you may get kind of a
specialization which doesn't include
other parts of it so it's a it's a I
think we're in that fascinating place
where we can't police I like what you
said - and the somewhere that if we get
to try and complete please tone too much
then we're missing something you need to
look at the content but tone does matter
and so does the ability to differentiate
so it's a it's a it's a fascinating
thing I think this is what you said you
believe that we can't really say too
much about what somebody else can or
can't talk about what they should or
shouldn't talk about you can say that
but we can't police the content of other
people's conversations yeah
can I can I just pick up on the notion
of tone because I mean I think you're
absolutely right we shouldn't be
policing time you should be policing
content but tone is it's not just it's
not just tone if someone is unable to
moderate their tone to keep their
discourse within and I'm not just
talking about narrow you know
fundamentalist parameters but I mean the
broadest you know social parameters of
polite discourse kind of thing if people
are unable to moderate their tone to
stay within those boundaries it
undermines something about their
character do you see what I mean it's so
it isn't just the tone itself that it's
it's the inability to moderate tone
points to a weakness in character my
willingness to listen to what they have
to say do you see what I mean oh it's a
it's an interesting notion
I'll just modify it slightly not so much
character but development so yeah okay
yes I agree I prefer that yes I prefer
that to this it kind of goes back to
Berkeley and the idea that
ah they're not able to see how to
moderate town or whatever in this month
they're not able to moderate and see
what see another perspective it's a it's
a challenge that is like okay so maybe
they just development into there maybe
the baby can maybe we can find some way
to to bridge that gap between them and
maybe we can't you know I think Chris is
know the Berkeley thing again is
thinking about that if everybody's
trying to help Marc play in Berkeley
just says you know what screw you
I like this leave me alone I don't have
a problem then then it's like okay what
do we do about that
is there something for us as a
collective to to intervene and try to
say something else needs to be done it's
a it's an interesting again nuance here
about the way that things fall out and
in collective and individual rights
right and I think that is the back to
the Berkeley like I have an actually I
can't remember the recall at that
episode but I think addiction in our
society is such a hot point because
we're all addicted to something we don't
see more addicted to game a right like I
mean we don't so then we reflected on
like well that's a heroin user and how
dare they and how like they're not
picking that over their kids well there
you are you picking it you're picking
your job you don't I mean like your job
over your kid you're picking like we
were being in in my addiction and I own
my addictions at least the ones I'm not
blind to its needy on pot and it's like
and yet they're there for a reason they
are like they'll not in Star Trek time
right if I'm in game B and I still have
that that I need to even look deeper
because it's like it's covering up pain
that isn't even my painting like my pain
I can deal with and I'm learning to deal
with the other stuff but it's like there
is something there and for outside
people to be like well then just don't
do it just have willpower and don't do
it I'm like it's not that simple because
it's I'm getting something out of it and
there's nowhere else to kind of like it
numbs the pain the actual physical pain
and like you know like there's so if he
was like no I'm this is where I am right
now
then I guess as star flee they feel like
we're dropping you off at the next
planet you're not really committed to
your to this but if they can put
pinpoint
what the actual effect is on them
instead of just like you're not allowed
to have addictions you're not allowed to
be stuck in that I think there is there
and then letting the person be empowered
to come out of it to be like okay that
was a fun three months on the holodeck
not need to eat oh you don't need to
it's costing me something and then they
can come out of it right
because if what's costing you is the
love and affection of your family and
friends it's the cost in and of itself
is the reason to have more of it right
as opposed to listen we love you we
maybe can't even be with you and your
addiction but we love you we're here for
you when you're done or we're here for
you in between time we don't want you to
show up hi but like we're here for you
when you're sober or whatever that they
need boundaries too but like it isn't
all that we need people not to be
addicted it's their thing their journey
and so how can we be present for them in
that in the most empowering way for them
without putting our you know there's a
really interesting point here which is I
thought about it in the past and it's
just coming up now is that what I
imagine game B is going to be better at
is actually being aware of our
externalities and minimizing the
externalities and this way there are
some relational externalities I say I
say my addictions are fine but I'm not
paying attention to the impact on my
family organizationally we say plastic
fine but we're not paying attention to
the extreme elegies on the environment
you know there are lots of things that
it's easy to say well it's fine but I'm
not really paying attention to the
larger cost of it it seems like I don't
see the problem so it's not my problem
to deal with but if there is a way that
we can actually collectively
reflectively see the impact that we're
having and notice that this behavior is
tied to this thing and there's a way to
a way to manage that you know how are
you responding to that impact if you're
not then we need to have a conversation
have do something we need in it at some
point intervene perhaps but there's
something that is based on the actual
aspect of that I think it's over I think
it's some it is sci-fi and kind of too
optimistic to believe that we can
monitor monitor everything and have a
real good
objective view on what the impacts that
we're having us but I think we can start
to move in that direction and we have
the capacity to do that today to much
bigger degree and that kind of honest
feedback is what's essential if we're
going to not fall into self-deception at
an individual or collective level so I
think there's something of just being
much more aware of what what's happening
when I'm back I'm having and being being
able to face that to being able to
integrate that feedback hmm of this - so
you did allude to this but there is a
very limited degree I think to which we
can be fully cognizant of the impact of
the impact of the impact of the impact
of the impact you know what I mean
certainly not personalized I mean in
terms of pollution into the environment
that's that's that's much clearer but
you know in certainly in terms of
actions taken choices made in our
personal lives and how those ripple out
I think it's dangerous is the word that
came to mind but that sounds like
overstating it but it I think to try and
take all of those consequences of all of
those consequences of all of those
consequences into account could drive
you absolutely insane and paralyze you
never actually do anything in the world
you know what I mean for fear of desert
does that make sense it doesn't just
there's a there's an interesting notion
of this I think that that's right that
carrying out too far is dangerous and
counterproductive but I don't think you
actually need to go out very far to
start seeing the benefit of that you
know and I think about this again
John Berwick ian is a notion of
relevance realization the way that we
focus on what is important to pay
attention to so for instance a lot of
people are scared to fly but they're not
scared to drive but if you look at the
statistics I mean that's irrational
that's an irrational thing that is
that's you know you don't recognize the
data and you're sort of blind - they
seem they seem woefully different or
tragically different and they're not
there you know that the bias there is
because of a blindness to the impact so
it's just one layer that you have to
look at and then once that gate becomes
integrated do you become more complex
and dealing with that and the way that
we navigate the world does that we
filter
attention to you but we filter with a
kind of bias and blindness that doesn't
include all of that all that potential
feedback that we could be getting I
think both sides like if if you're
scared of plane travel and I manage to
give you the data that shows well it's
safer compared to driving in your car my
intention is that you stop being scared
of planes but the actual impact could
very much be like aw crap but never
getting in a vehicle right like it's
still over like you no doubt it doesn't
necessarily get you there like I mean I
am very conscious of what what the cost
of my illness and the cost of my
addictions has on my child there is
never a point where you can get the
perfect Parenthood like you're never
there and yet that that paralysis
analysis well if I don't do this it's it
stops me from doing anything or when I
can sit with it and be like listen your
kids went camping your kids been to
Disneyland look at all the things she
has had you can't compare them to the
people with a higher echoed
socioeconomic status that have two
parents that are you know both worki and
both like right that does it it doesn't
compare but if you look at what you do
have instead of what you don't have it's
actually really amazing I do you know
like I read to my kid I do like there's
a lot that happens I'm like well my kid
has to get herself a snack because I
have to nap a lot right but there's food
in the house she never has to go out and
try to like beg for food or you know
what I mean like I'm not neglecting her
and it's in like someone needs to get
involved way and she's developing
independence because of it like there's
positive and negatives with everything
and - for the outside world to be like
okay well it's all it's all negative
right like you need to change cuz it's
negative one it's really hard to change
in that space I can only change from
loving and accepting words and then I am
like oh you're doing this too much or
you know what I mean like yes you're
you're fatigued and in pain but like you
can do a puzzle with her right like
finding ways to like add a little as
opposed to needing it to be perfect and
dealing with externalities I'm and I'm
realizing it's at fifty seven and a half
and I have to go like on the hour so
let's go yeah before yeah we're running
out of time I wanted to
- double-click on your point jubilee
about addiction though because this
issue of obviously there's a there's a
chasm between it being framed in terms
of you know criminality versus health
care right and this is part of the
paradigm shift we're going through the
war on drugs is still going on it's not
over even though it's legal in Canada
and it's locked in whatever it's like
there's still all sorts of stigma that
has to be fought and and you know the
whole the whole context has to be turned
upside down and you know again in terms
of the structural change on the table to
to to to do that is is Bernie Sanders
he's the only candidate the owner
there's no alternative all the others
are saying there's no really do have two
legs I have to get to in my body the
difference between it being medicine and
it being addiction they both exist
simultaneously and so where is one and
where is the other that's not for Bernie
said like in Canada it's not for anyone
else to decide it's for me like it's my
favorite size only enabled for you if
it's legal legalization of drugs but
does anyone want to do a closing thought
before we wrap it up and then you guys
continue on the one thing I'll say real
quick is that I think that there's some
aspect of the the views on this that get
weaponized by by I don't know if they're
my other parties or if it's just in that
collective in the way that it does
but then way there's social justice
warrior from a positive thing to and a
good thing is a way than which I think
we're being influenced by stuff and so
in a way it's the same debate tactic
something's convincing us we could we
swing wildly from one end to the other
and I'd like to I'd like to get myself
in the point of not reacting to the
flavor of something and actually get to
the substance I would very much like to
continue that discussion once Jubilee
switches us off if you don't mind
because there's I think there's much to
be unpacked here all right
well goodbye YouTube so you don't get to
watch that part I got to go friend worth
a massage and join us next week at the
same time for whatever we're talking
about that week friends you got it
medium join us here you can actually
watch
all right